<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://shameekvats.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://shameekvats.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-24T10:01:09+00:00</updated><id>https://shameekvats.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A personal website showcasing innovative projects to bring ideas to life. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Building Low Key: An Event Platform with Payment Gateway</title><link href="https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/building-lowkey-event-platform/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building Low Key: An Event Platform with Payment Gateway"/><published>2025-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/building-lowkey-event-platform</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/building-lowkey-event-platform/"><![CDATA[<p>When you’re organizing electronic music events, selling tickets online isn’t just a convenience—it’s essential. That’s the challenge that led to the creation of Low Key, a web platform designed specifically for managing event listings and ticket sales for electronic music gatherings. What started as a simple idea evolved into a journey through modern web hosting, payment integration, and the technical decisions that make online ticketing possible.</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center"> <div class="col-sm-8 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/web_dev_logos/lowkey_logo-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/web_dev_logos/lowkey_logo-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/web_dev_logos/lowkey_logo-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/web_dev_logos/lowkey_logo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Low Key Logo" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Low Key: Bringing electronic music events online </div> <h2 id="the-vision">The Vision</h2> <p>Low Key was created to serve electronic music event organizers who need a straightforward way to showcase their events and sell tickets online. The platform needed to be clean, easy to navigate, and most importantly, capable of handling real transactions. Each event listing includes detailed descriptions, pricing information, and the ability to purchase tickets across multiple tiers—whether attendees want general admission, VIP access, or early bird specials.</p> <p>The platform also needed flexibility in payment options. Not everyone uses the same payment method, so supporting various ways to pay was crucial for reaching a broader audience and making the ticket-buying process as smooth as possible.</p> <h2 id="why-not-github-pages">Why Not GitHub Pages?</h2> <p>My initial instinct was to host the site on GitHub Pages—it’s free, reliable, and perfect for static websites. However, there was one critical limitation: GitHub Pages doesn’t support backend functionality. Since payment processing requires server-side operations to securely handle transactions, I needed a hosting solution that could manage both the frontend display and backend payment logic.</p> <p>This is where Vercel entered the picture. Vercel provides the infrastructure needed to process payments securely while still offering the simplicity and speed of modern web hosting. It was the right tool for the job, even though it meant adjusting my original deployment plan.</p> <h2 id="building-with-the-basics">Building with the Basics</h2> <p>For the actual site construction, I kept things straightforward: HTML and CSS. There’s something satisfying about building with fundamental web technologies—no complex frameworks, no excessive dependencies. Just clean, semantic markup and styling that works across devices.</p> <p>This approach had several advantages:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Lightweight and fast</strong>: No heavy JavaScript frameworks meant quick load times</li> <li><strong>Easy to maintain</strong>: Simple codebase that’s easy to update</li> <li><strong>Full control</strong>: Direct manipulation of every element without fighting a framework’s opinions</li> <li><strong>Responsive design</strong>: CSS flexibility made it simple to ensure the site works on mobile devices, where many event-goers browse</li> </ul> <h2 id="the-payment-gateway-challenge">The Payment Gateway Challenge</h2> <p>Integrating Stripe as the payment gateway was, without question, the most significant challenge of the project. Payment processing isn’t just about collecting credit card numbers—it involves security, compliance, error handling, and user trust. Every step needs to work flawlessly because any hiccup directly impacts revenue and user experience.</p> <p>The integration required careful attention to:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Security</strong>: Ensuring payment data is transmitted securely</li> <li><strong>User experience</strong>: Making the checkout process intuitive and reassuring</li> <li><strong>Error handling</strong>: Gracefully managing declined cards or connection issues</li> <li><strong>Multiple payment methods</strong>: Supporting various ways customers prefer to pay</li> <li><strong>Ticket tiers</strong>: Properly routing different ticket types to the correct pricing</li> </ul> <p>Testing the payment flow repeatedly, handling edge cases, and ensuring everything worked smoothly across different scenarios took considerable time. But getting it right was non-negotiable—trust is everything when money changes hands.</p> <h2 id="bringing-it-all-together">Bringing It All Together</h2> <p>Once the payment gateway was functioning properly, the final pieces fell into place. The domain was purchased through a registrar and then connected to Vercel, pointing visitors to the hosted platform. The source code lives on GitHub, providing version control and a reliable backup of all development work.</p> <p>This setup created a complete pipeline: code changes pushed to GitHub trigger automatic deployments on Vercel, keeping the live site up to date with minimal friction. It’s the kind of workflow that makes ongoing maintenance and updates manageable.</p> <h2 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h2> <p>Building Low Key reinforced several important lessons about web development:</p> <p><strong>Choose the right tool for the job</strong>: GitHub Pages is excellent for static sites, but recognizing its limitations early saved significant time. Vercel’s capabilities aligned perfectly with the project’s needs.</p> <p><strong>Simplicity has value</strong>: Using HTML and CSS instead of a complex framework proved sufficient. Not every project needs the latest JavaScript library—sometimes the fundamentals are enough.</p> <p><strong>Payment integration is hard</strong>: What seems like a straightforward feature—”add a buy button”—turns out to involve numerous technical and security considerations. Respecting this complexity leads to better implementations.</p> <p><strong>User experience matters</strong>: The smoothest technical implementation means nothing if users find the interface confusing or the checkout process frustrating. Designing with the end user in mind was crucial.</p> <h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2> <p>Low Key now serves as a functional platform for electronic music events, handling everything from event discovery to ticket purchases. Future enhancements might include user accounts for tracking ticket purchases, email confirmations and reminders, or analytics for event organizers to understand their audience better.</p> <p>For now, though, the platform does what it set out to do: connect electronic music enthusiasts with events and provide a seamless way to secure their spot. You can see it in action at <a href="https://www.lowkey.lu/">lowkey.lu</a>.</p> <hr/> <p><em>This project demonstrated that effective web platforms don’t always require cutting-edge frameworks—sometimes clear purpose, solid fundamentals, and careful integration of key features like payment processing are all you need.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="web-development"/><category term="web-development"/><category term="event-management"/><category term="payment-gateway"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a ticket sales platform for electronic music events with integrated payment processing]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Early Steps in Industrial Robotics and Automation</title><link href="https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/industrial-robotics-automation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Early Steps in Industrial Robotics and Automation"/><published>2025-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/industrial-robotics-automation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/industrial-robotics-automation/"><![CDATA[<p>This project marks the beginning of my exploration into industrial robotics, a field where programming meets real-world machinery. I set up a simulated production line using a Dobot Magician robot, where a continuous conveyor belt delivers cubes in different colors. Programmed in Python, the robot picks up each cube, takes it to a detection point, and then sorts it into the correct container based on its color.</p> <p>To ensure smooth operation, I integrated a light sensor and an infrared sensor into the setup. The light sensor detects the cube’s color, while the infrared sensor controls the process by automatically turning it on or off when cubes are present. Working with three distinct colors not only demonstrates the basics of automation, but also fuels my curiosity for merging robotics with digital programming. This project is an exciting early step in refining my skills in Python-driven automation.</p> <h2 id="the-setup">The Setup</h2> <p>The automated production line consists of:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Dobot Magician robotic arm</strong>: A versatile 4-axis robotic arm ideal for educational and light industrial applications</li> <li><strong>Continuous conveyor belt</strong>: Delivers colored cubes to the detection point</li> <li><strong>Light sensor</strong>: Identifies the color of each cube (red, green, or blue)</li> <li><strong>Infrared sensor</strong>: Detects cube presence and controls process flow</li> <li><strong>Python control system</strong>: Orchestrates the entire operation</li> </ul> <h2 id="how-it-works">How It Works</h2> <p>The workflow is straightforward but demonstrates key automation principles:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Detection</strong>: The infrared sensor detects when a cube arrives on the conveyor</li> <li><strong>Color Recognition</strong>: The light sensor identifies the cube’s color</li> <li><strong>Pick-and-Place</strong>: The robot picks up the cube and moves it to the sorting area</li> <li><strong>Sorting</strong>: Based on color data, the robot places the cube in the corresponding container</li> <li><strong>Reset</strong>: The system returns to standby mode, ready for the next cube</li> </ol> <h2 id="technical-challenges">Technical Challenges</h2> <p>Working with real hardware presented interesting challenges:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Sensor Calibration</strong>: Getting accurate color detection required careful calibration of the light sensor</li> <li><strong>Timing Synchronization</strong>: Coordinating the conveyor belt speed with robot movements</li> <li><strong>Error Handling</strong>: Implementing fallback logic when sensors provide ambiguous readings</li> </ul> <h2 id="lessons-learned">Lessons Learned</h2> <p>This project taught me valuable lessons about the intersection of software and hardware:</p> <ul> <li>The importance of robust error handling in physical systems</li> <li>How sensor data can be unreliable and requires filtering</li> <li>The value of incremental testing when working with robotics</li> <li>Python’s versatility in controlling industrial hardware</li> </ul> <h2 id="the-result">The Result</h2> <p>Below is a video showcasing the setup in action:</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center"> <div class="col-sm-12 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <video controls="" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1"> <source src="/assets/img/project_robotics/industrial_robotics.mp4" type="video/mp4"/> Your browser does not support the video tag. </video> </div> </div> <h2 id="next-steps">Next Steps</h2> <p>This foundational project has opened doors to more advanced automation concepts. Future explorations might include:</p> <ul> <li>Integrating computer vision for more complex object recognition</li> <li>Implementing quality control checks during the sorting process</li> <li>Scaling to multi-robot coordination</li> <li>Adding machine learning for adaptive sorting algorithms</li> </ul> <hr/> <p><em>This project was completed as an introduction to industrial automation and represents my early steps in merging robotics with digital programming.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="engineering"/><category term="robotics"/><category term="automation"/><category term="python"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up a simulated production line with Python and Dobot Magician]]></summary></entry></feed>