<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://shameekvats.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://shameekvats.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-25T11:43:21+00:00</updated><id>https://shameekvats.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A personal website showcasing innovative projects to bring ideas to life. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Breathing New Life into a Surface Go 3 with Ubuntu</title><link href="https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/ubuntu-surface-go-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breathing New Life into a Surface Go 3 with Ubuntu"/><published>2025-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/ubuntu-surface-go-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/ubuntu-surface-go-3/"><![CDATA[<p>The Microsoft Surface Go 3 is an interesting piece of hardware—compact, portable, and versatile as both a laptop and tablet. However, running Windows 11 on it can feel sluggish due to its modest specifications. This led me to an interesting experiment: installing Ubuntu Linux on the Surface Go 3. The result? A significantly more responsive device that’s perfect for everyday tasks, browsing, and light development work.</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/surface-ubuntu-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/surface-ubuntu-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/surface-ubuntu-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/surface-ubuntu.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Ubuntu running on Surface Go 3" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Ubuntu brings new life to the Surface Go 3 </div> <h2 id="why-ubuntu-on-surface-go-3">Why Ubuntu on Surface Go 3?</h2> <p>With Windows 10 support ending in October 2025 and Windows 11 being somewhat demanding on older hardware, Linux presents an excellent alternative to keep perfectly functional devices out of landfills. The Surface Go 3, while not a powerhouse, has enough capability to run a lightweight Linux distribution smoothly.</p> <p>Ubuntu was my distribution of choice for several reasons:</p> <ul> <li>Wide hardware support and active community</li> <li>Excellent documentation and troubleshooting resources</li> <li>Regular security updates and LTS (Long Term Support) versions</li> <li>Familiar interface for those transitioning from Windows</li> </ul> <p>The Surface Go 3’s hardware—with its modest RAM and processor—actually benefits from Ubuntu’s lighter resource footprint compared to Windows 11.</p> <h2 id="prerequisites">Prerequisites</h2> <p>Before beginning the installation, you’ll need:</p> <ul> <li>A USB drive (at least 4GB)</li> <li>The Surface Go 3 itself</li> <li>Another computer to create the bootable USB (I used a Mac)</li> <li>A USB-C to USB-A adapter (for connecting the USB drive to the Surface)</li> <li>Patience and time to complete the process</li> <li><strong>Important</strong>: Backup any data on your Surface Go 3—this process will erase everything!</li> </ul> <h2 id="step-1-creating-a-bootable-usb-drive">Step 1: Creating a Bootable USB Drive</h2> <p>The first step is creating a bootable USB drive with Ubuntu on it. I used <a href="https://etcher.balena.io/">Balena Etcher</a> on my Mac, which makes the process straightforward:</p> <ol> <li>Download the latest <a href="https://ubuntu.com/download/desktop">Ubuntu Desktop ISO</a> from the official website</li> <li>Download and install <a href="https://etcher.balena.io/">Balena Etcher</a></li> <li>Insert your USB drive</li> <li>Open Balena Etcher and select the Ubuntu ISO file</li> <li>Select your USB drive as the target</li> <li>Click “Flash!” and wait for the process to complete</li> </ol> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-12 mt-3"> <div class="alert alert-warning" role="alert"> <strong>Note:</strong> The flashing process will erase all data on the USB drive. Make sure you've backed up any important files from it first. </div> </div> </div> <p>Alternative tools for creating bootable USB drives include <a href="https://rufus.ie/">Rufus</a> (Windows) or the command-line <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dd</code> utility on Linux. If you’re comfortable with the terminal, check out this <a href="https://linuxiac.com/how-to-create-bootable-usb-drive-using-dd-command/">guide on using dd</a>.</p> <h2 id="step-2-accessing-the-surface-go-3-boot-menu">Step 2: Accessing the Surface Go 3 Boot Menu</h2> <p>Unlike traditional PCs, the Surface Go 3 has its own unique method for accessing the boot menu and UEFI settings. Here’s how to prepare your Surface for Ubuntu installation:</p> <h3 id="disable-secure-boot">Disable Secure Boot</h3> <ol> <li><strong>Power off your Surface Go 3 completely</strong></li> <li><strong>Press and hold the Volume Up button</strong></li> <li><strong>While still holding Volume Up, press and release the Power button</strong></li> <li>Continue holding Volume Up until the Surface UEFI screen appears</li> </ol> <p>Once in the UEFI:</p> <ol> <li>Navigate to <strong>“Security”</strong> tab</li> <li>Find <strong>“Secure Boot”</strong> settings</li> <li>Change from <strong>“Microsoft Only”</strong> to <strong>“None”</strong> or <strong>“Disabled”</strong></li> <li>Save changes and exit (or continue to the next step)</li> </ol> <h3 id="configure-boot-order">Configure Boot Order</h3> <p>While still in the UEFI menu:</p> <ol> <li>Navigate to <strong>“Boot Configuration”</strong></li> <li>Move <strong>“USB Storage”</strong> to the top of the boot order</li> <li>Save and exit</li> </ol> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-12 mt-3"> <div class="alert alert-info" role="alert"> <strong>Tip:</strong> After successful Ubuntu installation, you may need to return to UEFI and change Secure Boot to "Microsoft &amp; 3rd party CA" for optimal functionality. </div> </div> </div> <p>For a visual guide on accessing the Surface UEFI, check out this helpful <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6_EHEmz_j4o">video tutorial</a>.</p> <h2 id="step-3-installing-ubuntu-from-usb">Step 3: Installing Ubuntu from USB</h2> <p>With your bootable USB drive ready and the Surface configured to boot from USB, you’re ready to install Ubuntu:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Insert the USB drive</strong> into your Surface Go 3 (using the USB-C to USB-A adapter if needed)</li> <li><strong>Restart the Surface</strong>—it should automatically boot from the USB drive</li> <li><strong>Wait patiently</strong>—the Surface Go 3 isn’t the fastest device, so the initial boot from USB can take several minutes</li> <li>Eventually, you’ll see the Ubuntu boot menu with options to “Try Ubuntu” or “Install Ubuntu”</li> <li><strong>Select “Try Ubuntu”</strong> to test everything first, or go straight to installation</li> </ol> <h3 id="installation-process">Installation Process</h3> <p>Once Ubuntu loads, you’ll see an icon on the desktop labeled “Install Ubuntu.” Double-click it to begin:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Select your language</strong> and click “Continue”</li> <li><strong>Choose your keyboard layout</strong></li> <li><strong>Select installation type</strong>: <ul> <li>For a fresh install, choose “Erase disk and install Ubuntu”</li> <li>This will remove Windows completely and give Ubuntu full access to the disk</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Select your timezone</strong> and create your user account</li> <li><strong>Click “Install Now”</strong> and confirm the changes</li> <li>Wait for the installation to complete (this can take 20-30 minutes)</li> <li><strong>Restart</strong> when prompted and remove the USB drive</li> </ol> <p>The Ubuntu installer is quite intuitive, and the touch screen works throughout the installation process, which is a pleasant surprise.</p> <h2 id="step-4-initial-ubuntu-setup">Step 4: Initial Ubuntu Setup</h2> <p>After rebooting into your fresh Ubuntu installation, there are a few essential tasks:</p> <h3 id="install-system-updates">Install System Updates</h3> <p>The first thing Ubuntu will prompt you to do is install updates. Don’t skip this step—it includes important security patches and driver updates:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">sudo </span>apt update <span class="o">&amp;&amp;</span> <span class="nb">sudo </span>apt upgrade <span class="nt">-y</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This command updates the package list and upgrades all installed packages to their latest versions. You’ll need to enter your password when prompted.</p> <h3 id="check-hardware-functionality">Check Hardware Functionality</h3> <p>At this point, test the basic hardware:</p> <ul> <li>✅ Touch screen should work</li> <li>✅ Physical keyboard (if attached)</li> <li>✅ Wi-Fi connectivity</li> <li>✅ Bluetooth</li> <li>✅ USB ports</li> <li>✅ Audio output</li> <li>❌ Cameras may not work yet</li> <li>❌ Some touch features might be limited</li> </ul> <h2 id="step-5-installing-the-linux-surface-kernel">Step 5: Installing the Linux Surface Kernel</h2> <p>The standard Ubuntu kernel provides basic Surface support, but to unlock full functionality—especially for improved touch support, stylus input, and better power management—you’ll want to install the specialized <a href="https://github.com/linux-surface/linux-surface">Linux Surface kernel</a>.</p> <h3 id="what-is-the-linux-surface-kernel">What is the Linux Surface Kernel?</h3> <p>The linux-surface project is a community effort to provide enhanced Linux support for Microsoft Surface devices. It includes:</p> <ul> <li>Optimized drivers for Surface-specific hardware</li> <li>Improved touch and stylus input</li> <li>Better battery management</li> <li>Thermal management improvements</li> </ul> <h3 id="installation-steps">Installation Steps</h3> <p>Follow the installation instructions from the <a href="https://github.com/linux-surface/linux-surface/wiki/Installation-and-Setup#debian--ubuntu">official linux-surface installation guide for Debian/Ubuntu</a>:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># Add the repository key</span>
wget <span class="nt">-qO</span> - https://raw.githubusercontent.com/linux-surface/linux-surface/master/pkg/keys/surface.asc <span class="se">\</span>
    | gpg <span class="nt">--dearmor</span> | <span class="nb">sudo dd </span><span class="nv">of</span><span class="o">=</span>/etc/apt/trusted.gpg.d/linux-surface.gpg

<span class="c"># Add the repository</span>
<span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"deb [arch=amd64] https://pkg.surfacelinux.com/debian release main"</span> <span class="se">\</span>
    | <span class="nb">sudo tee</span> /etc/apt/sources.list.d/linux-surface.list

<span class="c"># Update package lists</span>
<span class="nb">sudo </span>apt update

<span class="c"># Install the Surface kernel and related packages</span>
<span class="nb">sudo </span>apt <span class="nb">install </span>linux-image-surface linux-headers-surface iptsd libwacom-surface

<span class="c"># Reboot to use the new kernel</span>
<span class="nb">sudo </span>reboot
</code></pre></div></div> <p>After rebooting, you can verify you’re running the Surface kernel:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">uname</span> <span class="nt">-r</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>You should see output containing “surface” in the kernel name, such as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6.x.x-surface</code>.</p> <p>For more detailed information and troubleshooting, refer to the <a href="https://github.com/linux-surface/linux-surface/wiki/Installation-and-Setup#debian--ubuntu">complete installation guide</a>.</p> <h2 id="step-6-optimizing-your-ubuntu-experience">Step 6: Optimizing Your Ubuntu Experience</h2> <p>To enhance your Ubuntu experience on the Surface Go 3, the linux-surface project provides additional configuration options and tweaks. These include:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Virtual keyboard improvements</strong> for better tablet mode functionality</li> <li><strong>Touch scrolling enhancements</strong> for smoother navigation</li> <li><strong>Power management optimizations</strong> to extend battery life</li> <li><strong>Thermal management configurations</strong> to prevent overheating</li> <li><strong>Application recommendations</strong> specific to Surface devices</li> </ul> <p>For detailed optimization guides and configurations, visit the <a href="https://github.com/linux-surface/linux-surface/tree/master/contrib">linux-surface contrib directory</a> which contains scripts, tweaks, and configuration examples to improve your Linux experience on Surface devices.</p> <p>You can customize these based on your specific preferences and use case.</p> <h2 id="troubleshooting-common-issues">Troubleshooting Common Issues</h2> <p>If you encounter issues during or after installation, here are some common problems and general guidance:</p> <h3 id="touch-screen-not-working-during-installation">Touch Screen Not Working During Installation</h3> <p>This is unusual as the touch screen should work from the first installation screen. Ensure you’re using a recent Ubuntu ISO (22.04 LTS or newer).</p> <h3 id="wi-fi-not-connecting">Wi-Fi Not Connecting</h3> <p>Check if your Wi-Fi adapter is detected and try restarting the Network Manager. If problems persist, search for your specific Wi-Fi chipset in the Ubuntu forums.</p> <h3 id="stylus-pen-not-working">Stylus Pen Not Working</h3> <p>After installing the linux-surface kernel, the Surface Pen should work automatically. If not, ensure the wacom support packages are installed.</p> <h3 id="system-not-booting-to-ubuntu">System Not Booting to Ubuntu</h3> <p>You may need to adjust boot order in UEFI or check that Secure Boot is properly configured. Boot into UEFI (Volume Up + Power) and verify settings.</p> <p>For more detailed troubleshooting and device-specific issues, visit:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://github.com/linux-surface/linux-surface/wiki">Linux Surface Wiki</a></li> <li><a href="https://github.com/linux-surface/linux-surface/issues">Linux Surface GitHub Issues</a></li> <li><a href="https://ubuntuforums.org/">Ubuntu Forums</a></li> </ul> <h2 id="my-experience-performance-and-daily-use">My Experience: Performance and Daily Use</h2> <p>After completing the installation and setup, the Surface Go 3 running Ubuntu feels significantly more responsive than it did with Windows 11. Applications launch faster, multitasking is smoother, and the overall system feels less sluggish.</p> <h3 id="what-works-well">What Works Well:</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Web browsing</strong>: Firefox and Chrome run smoothly</li> <li><strong>Light development</strong>: VS Code works great for coding</li> <li><strong>Media consumption</strong>: YouTube, streaming services all work perfectly</li> <li><strong>Touch screen</strong>: Responsive and accurate</li> <li><strong>Battery life</strong>: Comparable to or better than Windows 11</li> <li><strong>System responsiveness</strong>: Noticeably faster than Windows 11</li> <li><strong>Multitasking</strong>: Handles multiple applications smoothly</li> </ul> <p>For my use case—casual browsing, reading documentation, light coding, and media consumption—the Surface Go 3 running Ubuntu is now a perfectly capable device that I enjoy using.</p> <h2 id="resources-and-references">Resources and References</h2> <p>Throughout this installation journey, I found these resources invaluable:</p> <h3 id="official-documentation">Official Documentation</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://ubuntu.com/download/desktop">Ubuntu Desktop Download</a></li> <li><a href="https://github.com/linux-surface/linux-surface">Linux Surface GitHub Repository</a></li> <li><a href="https://github.com/linux-surface/linux-surface/wiki/Installation-and-Setup">Linux Surface Installation Guide</a></li> <li><a href="https://github.com/linux-surface/linux-surface/wiki/Camera-Support">Linux Surface Camera Support</a></li> </ul> <h3 id="tools-used">Tools Used</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://etcher.balena.io/">Balena Etcher</a> - USB creation tool</li> <li><a href="https://rufus.ie/">Rufus</a> - Alternative USB creation tool (Windows)</li> </ul> <h3 id="helpful-blog-posts">Helpful Blog Posts</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://theprivacydad.com/ubuntu-on-a-windows-surface-go-3/">The Privacy Dad’s Guide to Ubuntu on Surface Go 3</a></li> <li><a href="https://blog.lhotka.net/2025/04/22/Running-Linux-on-My-Surface-Go">Rockford Lhotka’s Experience Running Linux on Surface Go</a></li> </ul> <h3 id="video-tutorials">Video Tutorials</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6_EHEmz_j4o">How to Access Surface UEFI</a></li> <li><a href="https://linuxiac.com/how-to-create-bootable-usb-drive-using-dd-command/">Creating Bootable USB with dd</a></li> </ul> <h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2> <p>Installing Ubuntu on the Surface Go 3 breathes new life into what many might consider an underpowered Windows device. While there are some trade-offs—primarily around camera quality and some advanced stylus features—the improvements in system responsiveness and overall user experience more than make up for these limitations.</p> <p>If you have a Surface Go 3 (or similar Surface device) gathering dust because Windows 11 feels too slow, I highly recommend giving Ubuntu a try. The installation process is straightforward, well-documented, and the result is a device that’s genuinely pleasant to use for everyday tasks.</p> <p>The Linux community’s work on the linux-surface project demonstrates the power of open-source collaboration, and it’s exciting to see Microsoft hardware running so well on a completely different operating system. Plus, you’re keeping a perfectly functional device out of a landfill—a win for both your productivity and the environment.</p> <hr/> <p><em>Have you tried installing Linux on a Surface device? What was your experience? Feel free to reach out and share your story!</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="linux"/><category term="linux"/><category term="ubuntu"/><category term="surface"/><category term="hardware"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A comprehensive guide to installing Ubuntu on a Microsoft Surface Go 3 tablet]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building Low Key: An Event Platform with Payment Gateway</title><link href="https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/building-lowkey-event-platform/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building Low Key: An Event Platform with Payment Gateway"/><published>2025-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/building-lowkey-event-platform</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/building-lowkey-event-platform/"><![CDATA[<p>When you’re organizing electronic music events, selling tickets online isn’t just a convenience—it’s essential. That’s the challenge that led to the creation of Low Key, a web platform designed specifically for managing event listings and ticket sales for electronic music gatherings. What started as a simple idea evolved into a journey through modern web hosting, payment integration, and the technical decisions that make online ticketing possible.</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center"> <div class="col-sm-8 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/web_dev_logos/lowkey_logo-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/web_dev_logos/lowkey_logo-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/web_dev_logos/lowkey_logo-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/web_dev_logos/lowkey_logo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Low Key Logo" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Low Key: Bringing electronic music events online </div> <h2 id="the-vision">The Vision</h2> <p>Low Key was created to serve electronic music event organizers who need a straightforward way to showcase their events and sell tickets online. The platform needed to be clean, easy to navigate, and most importantly, capable of handling real transactions. Each event listing includes detailed descriptions, pricing information, and the ability to purchase tickets across multiple tiers—whether attendees want general admission, VIP access, or early bird specials.</p> <p>The platform also needed flexibility in payment options. Not everyone uses the same payment method, so supporting various ways to pay was crucial for reaching a broader audience and making the ticket-buying process as smooth as possible.</p> <h2 id="why-not-github-pages">Why Not GitHub Pages?</h2> <p>My initial instinct was to host the site on GitHub Pages—it’s free, reliable, and perfect for static websites. However, there was one critical limitation: GitHub Pages doesn’t support backend functionality. Since payment processing requires server-side operations to securely handle transactions, I needed a hosting solution that could manage both the frontend display and backend payment logic.</p> <p>This is where Vercel entered the picture. Vercel provides the infrastructure needed to process payments securely while still offering the simplicity and speed of modern web hosting. It was the right tool for the job, even though it meant adjusting my original deployment plan.</p> <h2 id="building-with-the-basics">Building with the Basics</h2> <p>For the actual site construction, I kept things straightforward: HTML and CSS. There’s something satisfying about building with fundamental web technologies—no complex frameworks, no excessive dependencies. Just clean, semantic markup and styling that works across devices.</p> <p>This approach had several advantages:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Lightweight and fast</strong>: No heavy JavaScript frameworks meant quick load times</li> <li><strong>Easy to maintain</strong>: Simple codebase that’s easy to update</li> <li><strong>Full control</strong>: Direct manipulation of every element without fighting a framework’s opinions</li> <li><strong>Responsive design</strong>: CSS flexibility made it simple to ensure the site works on mobile devices, where many event-goers browse</li> </ul> <h2 id="the-payment-gateway-challenge">The Payment Gateway Challenge</h2> <p>Integrating Stripe as the payment gateway was, without question, the most significant challenge of the project. Payment processing isn’t just about collecting credit card numbers—it involves security, compliance, error handling, and user trust. Every step needs to work flawlessly because any hiccup directly impacts revenue and user experience.</p> <p>The integration required careful attention to:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Security</strong>: Ensuring payment data is transmitted securely</li> <li><strong>User experience</strong>: Making the checkout process intuitive and reassuring</li> <li><strong>Error handling</strong>: Gracefully managing declined cards or connection issues</li> <li><strong>Multiple payment methods</strong>: Supporting various ways customers prefer to pay</li> <li><strong>Ticket tiers</strong>: Properly routing different ticket types to the correct pricing</li> </ul> <p>Testing the payment flow repeatedly, handling edge cases, and ensuring everything worked smoothly across different scenarios took considerable time. But getting it right was non-negotiable—trust is everything when money changes hands.</p> <h2 id="bringing-it-all-together">Bringing It All Together</h2> <p>Once the payment gateway was functioning properly, the final pieces fell into place. The domain was purchased through a registrar and then connected to Vercel, pointing visitors to the hosted platform. The source code lives on GitHub, providing version control and a reliable backup of all development work.</p> <p>This setup created a complete pipeline: code changes pushed to GitHub trigger automatic deployments on Vercel, keeping the live site up to date with minimal friction. It’s the kind of workflow that makes ongoing maintenance and updates manageable.</p> <h2 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h2> <p>Building Low Key reinforced several important lessons about web development:</p> <p><strong>Choose the right tool for the job</strong>: GitHub Pages is excellent for static sites, but recognizing its limitations early saved significant time. Vercel’s capabilities aligned perfectly with the project’s needs.</p> <p><strong>Simplicity has value</strong>: Using HTML and CSS instead of a complex framework proved sufficient. Not every project needs the latest JavaScript library—sometimes the fundamentals are enough.</p> <p><strong>Payment integration is hard</strong>: What seems like a straightforward feature—”add a buy button”—turns out to involve numerous technical and security considerations. Respecting this complexity leads to better implementations.</p> <p><strong>User experience matters</strong>: The smoothest technical implementation means nothing if users find the interface confusing or the checkout process frustrating. Designing with the end user in mind was crucial.</p> <h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2> <p>Low Key now serves as a functional platform for electronic music events, handling everything from event discovery to ticket purchases. Future enhancements might include user accounts for tracking ticket purchases, email confirmations and reminders, or analytics for event organizers to understand their audience better.</p> <p>For now, though, the platform does what it set out to do: connect electronic music enthusiasts with events and provide a seamless way to secure their spot. You can see it in action at <a href="https://www.lowkey.lu/">lowkey.lu</a>.</p> <hr/> <p><em>This project demonstrated that effective web platforms don’t always require cutting-edge frameworks—sometimes clear purpose, solid fundamentals, and careful integration of key features like payment processing are all you need.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="web-development"/><category term="web-development"/><category term="event-management"/><category term="payment-gateway"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a ticket sales platform for electronic music events with integrated payment processing]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Early Steps in Industrial Robotics and Automation</title><link href="https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/industrial-robotics-automation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Early Steps in Industrial Robotics and Automation"/><published>2025-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/industrial-robotics-automation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shameekvats.github.io/blog/2025/industrial-robotics-automation/"><![CDATA[<p>This project marks the beginning of my exploration into industrial robotics, a field where programming meets real-world machinery. I set up a simulated production line using a Dobot Magician robot, where a continuous conveyor belt delivers cubes in different colors. Programmed in Python, the robot picks up each cube, takes it to a detection point, and then sorts it into the correct container based on its color.</p> <p>To ensure smooth operation, I integrated a light sensor and an infrared sensor into the setup. The light sensor detects the cube’s color, while the infrared sensor controls the process by automatically turning it on or off when cubes are present. Working with three distinct colors not only demonstrates the basics of automation, but also fuels my curiosity for merging robotics with digital programming. This project is an exciting early step in refining my skills in Python-driven automation.</p> <h2 id="the-setup">The Setup</h2> <p>The automated production line consists of:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Dobot Magician robotic arm</strong>: A versatile 4-axis robotic arm ideal for educational and light industrial applications</li> <li><strong>Continuous conveyor belt</strong>: Delivers colored cubes to the detection point</li> <li><strong>Light sensor</strong>: Identifies the color of each cube (red, green, or blue)</li> <li><strong>Infrared sensor</strong>: Detects cube presence and controls process flow</li> <li><strong>Python control system</strong>: Orchestrates the entire operation</li> </ul> <h2 id="how-it-works">How It Works</h2> <p>The workflow is straightforward but demonstrates key automation principles:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Detection</strong>: The infrared sensor detects when a cube arrives on the conveyor</li> <li><strong>Color Recognition</strong>: The light sensor identifies the cube’s color</li> <li><strong>Pick-and-Place</strong>: The robot picks up the cube and moves it to the sorting area</li> <li><strong>Sorting</strong>: Based on color data, the robot places the cube in the corresponding container</li> <li><strong>Reset</strong>: The system returns to standby mode, ready for the next cube</li> </ol> <h2 id="technical-challenges">Technical Challenges</h2> <p>Working with real hardware presented interesting challenges:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Sensor Calibration</strong>: Getting accurate color detection required careful calibration of the light sensor</li> <li><strong>Timing Synchronization</strong>: Coordinating the conveyor belt speed with robot movements</li> <li><strong>Error Handling</strong>: Implementing fallback logic when sensors provide ambiguous readings</li> </ul> <h2 id="lessons-learned">Lessons Learned</h2> <p>This project taught me valuable lessons about the intersection of software and hardware:</p> <ul> <li>The importance of robust error handling in physical systems</li> <li>How sensor data can be unreliable and requires filtering</li> <li>The value of incremental testing when working with robotics</li> <li>Python’s versatility in controlling industrial hardware</li> </ul> <h2 id="the-result">The Result</h2> <p>Below is a video showcasing the setup in action:</p> <div class="row justify-content-sm-center"> <div class="col-sm-12 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <video controls="" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1"> <source src="/assets/img/project_robotics/industrial_robotics.mp4" type="video/mp4"/> Your browser does not support the video tag. </video> </div> </div> <h2 id="next-steps">Next Steps</h2> <p>This foundational project has opened doors to more advanced automation concepts. Future explorations might include:</p> <ul> <li>Integrating computer vision for more complex object recognition</li> <li>Implementing quality control checks during the sorting process</li> <li>Scaling to multi-robot coordination</li> <li>Adding machine learning for adaptive sorting algorithms</li> </ul> <hr/> <p><em>This project was completed as an introduction to industrial automation and represents my early steps in merging robotics with digital programming.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="engineering"/><category term="robotics"/><category term="automation"/><category term="python"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up a simulated production line with Python and Dobot Magician]]></summary></entry></feed>